We start today at the bottom of ה' עמוד א' Hey Amud
Aleph we will try to cover דף ו' Daf Vav today but
we start at the very bottom of ה' עמוד א' Hey Amud
Aleph very last line תיובתא דרבנן תיובתא Tiyuvta DeRabanan Tiyuvta where we
have the ברייתא Braita that says that a מומר Mumar can be
שוחט Shochet and we have two explanations for it. One explanation is
a מומר אוכל נבילות לתיאבון Mumar Ochel Neveilos Leteavon somebody who basically
doesn't care about כשרות Kashrus and the other explanation is a real
מומר Mumar somebody who even is an idolater and which of the
and the גמרא Gemara finally rejected that second explanation based on a
ברייתא Braita that also put in the same category somebody who is
a public violator of שבת. Shabbat. So this is the classic sort
of approach that we are familiar with that an idolater and a
violator of שבת Shabbat is categorically excluded from a range of מצוות
Mitzvos and is perceived as like a real an invalidity of the
person's status and in the end we're left with the explanation that
if somebody just violates a single thing even if it's כשרות Kashrus
they still could be trusted to do the שחיטה Shechita correctly under
the right circumstances. So that is where we are right now where
what we have not excluded the אוכל נבילות לתיאבון Ochel Neveilos Leteavon
we have excluded the idolater and the public violator of שבת Shabbat
and that is certainly where our tradition where the הלכה Halacha is
for us. So now we pick up on the very last line.
The גמרא Gemara says the following. והא מהכא נפקא מהתם נפקא Veha
Meihacha Nafka Meihasam Nafka do we really learn it from there from
this verse about מכם Mikem to exclude a מומר Mumar from bringing
sacrifices? We really learn it from another פסוק Pasuk that a מומר
Mumar is excluded from bringing sacrifices. Where is that? מעם הארץ Me'am
Ha'aretz it says that if somebody brings a sin offering from the
people of the land and the מ' Mem means from not all
פרט למומר Prat Lemumar so not all of the people of the
land it excludes somebody that is a violator or a rebel that
that person does not bring a sin offering. ר' שמעון יוסי אומר
Rabbi Shimon Yossi Omer Rabbi Shimon Yossi says משום ר' שמעון Mishum
Rabbi Shimon in the name of Rabbi Shimon אשר לא תעשינה בשגגה
ואשם. Asher Lo Te'asenah Bishgaga Ve'ashem. The verse says that a person
does a sin that you would not normally do and you did
it in error and he is guilty. So from here we learn
out השב מידיעתו מביא קרבן על שגגתו Hashav Miyedi'ato Mevih Korban Al
Shgagato
that somebody that were he to not have been a שוגג Shogeg
were he to be aware of what he was doing incorrectly would
bring a קרבן Korban as a result of his error but אינו
שב מידיעתו Eino Shav Miyedi'ato somebody who would not normally
somebody who would not change his ways if he was aware that
he was doing something wrong so that person אינו מביא קרבן על
שגגתו Eino Mevih Korban Al Shgagato does not bring a קרבן Korban
for his error meaning if you would have done it you might
have sinned in error but if you would have sinned anyway even
had you not been in error even had
you
known the facts even had they you would have been prepared to
sin intentionally so that type of a person does not bring a
קרבן. Korban. I'm a person that I eat טרפה. Treifa. This time
I thought I was eating kosher and it happened to be טרפה.
Treifa. So I'm not going to bring a קרבן Korban because even
if I knew it was טרפה Treifa I would have eaten it.
That's what Rabbi Shimon says. So these are two people that are
excluded from being קרבן Korban somebody that's a מומר Mumar somebody that
sins regularly sins and somebody that would have done it anyway. So
the גמרא Gemara asks what's the difference. Let's take a look. ואמרינן
מאי בינייהו Veamrinan Mai Beinihu and we
said what's the difference both of them are saying that if a
person is a regular sinner you don't bring a קרבן. Korban. ואמר
רב המנונא מומר לאכול חלב והביא קרבן על הדם איכא בינייהו. Veamar
Rav Hamnuna Mumar Le'echol Cheilev Vehevi Korban Al Hadam Ika Beinihu. No
the difference is somebody that normally sins in one type of area
but he accidentally now sins in a different area. This person is
a regular eater of forbidden fat. That's the only thing he violates.
Other things he doesn't violate. This time it happened that he accidentally
ate blood okay which is another forbidden food and as תוספות Tosafot
points out it's a very linked forbidden food because the תורה Torah
prohibits fat and blood in the same way because they're both things
that are normally given from the sacrifices they're both punishable by כרת
Kares so it's in the same sort of universe of forbidden foods
but it's different. Okay but normally this person doesn't eat blood he
only eats fat. This time he ate blood by accident. So what's
the story? So does he bring a קרבן? Korban?
So the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell it out but the difference is
the following. If you say that the only reason you don't bring
a קרבן Korban is because you would have done it anyway then
this guy says I wouldn't have done it anyway if it were
fat I would have done it anyway but for blood that I
wouldn't have done. Oh so since you wouldn't have done it anyway
then you bring a קרבן Korban because normally you wouldn't have done
it and you only did it by an error. But if the
issue is you don't bring a קרבן Korban because you are a
מומר Mumar because your status as a person that's a regular sinner
so since you're a regular sinner of fat even though you're not
a regular sinner of blood since you are this habitual regular sinner
you're not going to bring a קרבן Korban regardless. תוספות Tosfos points
out that it's only because you're a habitual sinner in a linked
related area. Remember yesterday we said that just because a person if
we're not dealing with something like שבת Shabbos or עבודה זרה, Avoda
Zara, just because a person is a sinner for like eating non-kosher
food, does not generally invalidate them. So here we're not saying that
just because this person is a habitual sinner about חלב, cheilev, they're
generally invalidated. What they are though is is that they're excluded from
bringing sin offerings in this cluster of sins, cluster of behaviors. So
included in the cluster of behavior of חלב cheilev is also the
eating of דם, dam, even though you normally don't eat דם, dam,
but it's part of the same what I would say פרשה parsha
and therefore you're completely excluded from bringing a sin offering in that.
So anyway what do we have? We have before we excluded from
a sin offering a person that is a idolater and a שבת
Shabbos violator, that type of a thing is called a מומר mumar
and is categorically excluded. And now we've excluded from bringing a קרבן
korban somebody that either would have sinned anyway or somebody that would
have been at least you know been a habitual violator in this
area of behavior even if not in this particular thing. Okay and
that is so now the גמרא Gemara says why do I have
to exclude a מומר mumar in two cases? Now of course part
of the answer is that we're excluding different types of מומר, mumar,
but the גמרא'ס Gemara's bracketing that and says why do I need
two different ways, two different types of ways of excluding a מומר?
mumar? You had a question.
Are these people formally defined as מומרים mumarim if they are they
publicly addressed? I mean I have no idea.
That's a good question.
Yeah, there's no legal in that sense. So no they feel very,
now essentially they would kind of be out on their own like
closing of that?
No, I don't think it was anything like that. Not that I
know of, not that I know of.
In other words, rumor has it that.
Right, yeah, how would that status be established and so on? I
mean there is some discussion in הלכה halacha about like whether there
needs to be it have to be in front of a like
there has to have been testimony about this, does a בית דין
Beis Din have to be aware, how much like for the שבת
Shabbos violator in public, how do you define public? But I don't
think it meant that the person went around town with like a
big mark on his forehead or something like that. No no that
we know we never hear of. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
wants to know why do we have to exclude a מומר mumar
twice from bringing a קרבן? korban? So the גמרא Gemara says חד
בחטאת וחד בעולה וצריכא. chad be-chatas ve-chad be-olah u-tzricha. No cause one
excluded a person from a חטאת chatas and one excluded him from
an עולה olah and you need both cases. ואי אשמעינן חטאת, ve-ee
ashmeinan chatas, had it just said a חטאת, chatas, משום דכפרה היא,
mishum de-kapara hee, that that is for atonement.
So maybe you don't deserve atonement if you are such a willful
violator, so you're not deserving of atonement. אבל עולה, aval olah, but
if it was an עולה, olah, דדורון הוא, de-doron hu, that's a
gift to God, so you know that's not such an affront to
bring a gift even though you're a violator. אימא לקבל מיניה, eima
lekabel minei, maybe it should be accepted. ואי אשמעינן עולה, ve-ee ashmeinan
olah, had it just said we don't accept an עולה olah from
a מומר, mumar, from a from a habitual violator, משום דלאו חיובא
הוא, mishum de-lav chiyuva hu, he has no obligation, so therefore we
say you know he's going to be excluded from an עולה olah
because he's not entitled to bring it, he's a habitual violator and
he has no obligation to bring it. אבל חטאת, aval chatas, but
a sin offering, דחיובא הוא, de-chiyuva hu, that there is an obligation
to bring a sin offering, אימא לקבל מיניה, eima lekabel minei, maybe
that we should bring it from him, maybe that it's more insistent
that it should be brought and we're not so ready to exclude
him. Also as רש"י Rashi says we don't want him to benefit
just because he's a sinner he gets out of an obligation. צריכא,
tzricha, so it tells me both cases. Now again as you know
תוספות Tosfos points out they're not really the same. In one case
I exclude somebody that's a מומר mumar because he's really categorically excluded,
he's an idolater or a שבת Shabbos violator. In the other case
I'm excluding a מומר mumar because it's not appropriate to bring a
sin offering if you're a willful violator, or even if you're not
a willful violator of this itself, if you're a willful violator of
a related area of behavior. Okay, but anyway those are the two
ways in which we exclude מומר mumar from a קרבן. korban. Back
to our issue, more relevant for us is is that the type
of a person that is categorically excluded in general is the idolater
and the שבת Shabbos violator, but if you sin in a particular
area, even if it's the same area, even if it's כשרות, Kashrus,
given the right circumstances we might trust you to be a שוחט.
shochet. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues and it sort of
focuses now on a side point about the ברייתא Baraisa we quoted
before. It says וכל היכא דכתיב בהמה גרועה היא, ve-chol heicha de-chsiv
behemah geruah hee, if you remember the ברייתא Baraisa before said that
since the verse said a בהמה, behemah, that it certain said that
even people that are sinners like animals, they're as bad as animals,
even those people can bring קרבנות. korbanos. So it says does the
word בהמה behemah really mean a like an insult, people that are
like as bad as animals? והכתיב, ve-haksiv, I'll give you a place
where it says something positive. אדם ובהמה תושיע ה', adam u-behemah toshia
Hashem, man and beast God will save. So it's something good that
they're saved, it's not really used here as an insult, so or
you know as a derogatory term. And how do I know it?
Because here's how we explain it. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב, ve-amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אלו בני אדם שהן ערומין בדעת, elu benei
adam she-hein arumin be-da'as, this refers, this בהמה behemah that God saves,
to people that are clever in knowledge. sly in their intellect, ומשימים
עצמם כבהמה, umasimin atzmam k'behema,
and treat themselves like a בהמה, behema, meaning that they are very
humble and lowly and they're not arrogant, these are the people that
God will save. So here בהמה behema is used as a positive
connotation, that it means you are humble and, and so how come
we before assumed that the word בהמה behema means a, means a
what do you call it, means somebody that is, you know, means
a sinner? So the Gemara says: התם כתיב אדם ובהמה הכא בהמה
לחודיה כתיב. Hatam ketiv adam ubehema hacha behema lechudei ketiv. No,
there it says man and beast. So beast is connected to man,
so we're going to interpret it in a positive way, a type
of a human being that is humble like an animal, does not
you know, non-arrogant. When it just says בהמה behema by itself, then
we're going to interpret it in a negative way, as a sinner.
So the Gemara says: וכל היכא דכתיב אדם ובהמה מעליותא היא? Vechol
heicha deketiv adam ubehema ma'alyuta hi? So now it's going to not
let up. It says, oh, but now you're telling me that where
it says man and beast it's a positive? והא כתיב, Veha ketiv,
I'll give you another example where it's a negative. וזרעתי את בית
ישראל זרע אדם וזרע בהמה. Vezarati et beit Yisrael zera adam vezera
behema.
I will plant the house of Israel the planting of man, the
planting of animal. So what does this mean? I mean it's referring
to like that we're going to be spread out in the גלות,
Galut, but ultimately it's a positive that you know we'll sprout forth
and so on like the planting of a seed. And how do
we know that's a negative? Because the Gemara interprets this in סוטה
Sotah to say that this refers to people that are not learned
in Torah. So,
and God is saying whether they're scholars or whether they're ignoramuses I'm
going to spread them out and plant them and eventually they'll sprout
forth and they'll be very and they'll multiply. So there at least
we interpret the word בהמה behema in a negative to mean, you
know, ignoramuses, non-scholars. So the Gemara says: no, חלקי קרא זרע אדם
לחוד וזרע בהמה לחוד. Chalkei kra zera adam lechud vezera behema lechud.
There it's not linking אדם adam and בהמה. behema. The earlier verse
said אדם ובהמה, adam ubehema, so it really linked them. Here it
separates them: the planting of man, the planting of beast. So therefore
separate so we're going to interpret the word beast in a negative
way. Okay, so anyway that's just wrapping up the fact that we
interpreted beast to mean sinners, sometimes we interpret it negative, sometimes we
interpret it positive. Now we get back to our main theme. So
remember what has been our main theme? Our main theme now has
been focusing on the types of people that are not acceptable to
be שוחטים. shochtim. Or, not not acceptable, questionably acceptable. One was the
מומר, mumar, the regular violator of eating non-shechted meat. And there Rava
says, and that presumably is how we remain, that if you give
him a checked knife and there's really no incentive for him to
do it wrong, we can assume he'll do it right, even if
he's not observed, which is a pretty surprising thing. And now the
other person that we had been talking about was the כותי. Kuti.
And we had explored that also, the Samaritan, how much do you
assume that they do keep the laws, they don't keep the laws,
they keep them with scrupulousness, how do you make sure that they're
not trying to trip us up even if they keep it personally,
but the general upshot was also there as well that under the
right circumstances a כותי Kuti you can trust their שחיטה. shechita. Okay,
now we're going to revisit the case of שכותי. sheKuti. Let's take
a look. אמר רבי חנן אמר רבי יעקב אמר רבי יעקב בר
אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משום בר קפרא רבן גמליאל ובית
דינו נמנו על שחיטת כותי ואסרוה. Amar Rabbi Chanan amar Rabbi Yaakov
amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar
Kappara Rabban Gamliel uveit dino nimnu al shechitat Kuti ve'asruha.
Rabban Gamliel and his and his, you know, court took a vote,
reassessed the situation of the כותים Kutim and they made the שחיטה
shechita forbidden. We don't know why yet, but although before we said
it is okay, here we are now saying that they made a
decision to say the שחיטה shechita of a כותי Kuti is no
good. אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי יעקב בר אידי. Amar lei Rabbi
Zeira leRabbi Yaakov bar Idi. So Rabbi Zeira said to Rabbi Yaakov
bar Idi: שמא לא שמע רבי אלא בשאין ישראל עומד על גביו?
Shema lo shama Rabbi ela beshein Yisrael omed al gabav?
Maybe when you know, maybe that this report here was only because
this is Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi was the one who was reporting
it, so he said: are you sure that's what they said? Are
you sure they said that we can't trust a כותי? Kuti? Maybe
it only means when there's no direct observation, when you're not עומד
על גביו. omed al gabav. Because that we know that if you
have you need to be directly observing a כותי, Kuti, either directly
observing him or making sure that he's going to eat his own
meat. If he'll eat his own meat, then you can trust it.
But those were the two circumstances. So he says, maybe you don't
mean we completely invalidate it. Maybe you only mean we invalidate it
if you haven't observed him שחיטה shechting it. Is it possible that's
what you really were talking about, that that's what you really heard?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him. אמר ליה
דמי האי מרבנן כדלא גמר אינשי שמעתא. Amar lei dami hai merabbanan
kedelo gamir inshi shma'ata. He says, it seems to me that this
rabbi, meaning you who asked that question, it's like you never learned
anything in your life. You know, what type of stupid question is
that? בשאין ישראל עומד על גביו למימרא בעי? Beshein Yisrael omed al
gabav lemeimra ba'ei? If he was not being observed, would it have
required a statement at all? Meaning we've always taken for granted that
a כותי Kuti is only good either if it's under direct observation
or if you make him eat from the meat itself. So if
I am coming and telling you that there was a teaching going
all the way back that Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין Beit
Din said a כותי Kuti is not good, I am obviously not
talking that there're, you know, obviously if there was no direct observation
it would be... purposeless to say it. We all know that you
need direct observation. So if I am telling you a כותי Kuti
is no good, it means even with direct observation they've decided to
not allow the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי. Kuti. Now that really
raises a serious question, because if it's with direct observation, so what
could go wrong? You're directly looking at it, right? Even a חרש
שוטה וקטן Cheresh Shoteh v'Katan with direct observation is okay. So what
could be wrong with the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti if
you are directly observing? And the only real possibility is we only
know of one category of people that even with direct observation it's
no good. And who is that? That is a non-Jew, because a
non-Jew, even if it's technically done one hundred percent correctly, is categorically
excluded and the שחיטה Shechita of a non-Jew is invalid. It needs
to be shechted by a Jew. So here if they're saying that
the shechting of a כותי Kuti is not good even with direct
observation, what it implicitly is saying is they are categorizing כותים Kutim
as non-Jews. And that is what we are going to get to.
Okay. So he says, but his immediate response is what a stupid
question that was. Of course it's direct observation, otherwise you wouldn't need
to say anything.
So קבלה מיניה או לא קבלה מיניה? kablah minei o lo kablah
minei? Did he accept that response or not? Was he willing to
accept the idea that the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti is
not good even with direct observation? So תא שמע, tashma, come and
hear, דאמר רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר רב אסי, d'amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak amar Rav Assi, אני ראיתי את רבי יוחנן שאכל משחיטת
כותי. ani ra'iti et Rabbi Yochanan she'achal mishchitat Kuti. I saw Rabbi
Yochanan who was prepared to eat from the shechting of a כותי,
Kuti, this is even after, obviously after רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and
בית דינו, beis dino, and after this teaching that we just had.
So where are we? שאכל משחיטת
כותי. she'achal mishchitat Kuti. אף רב אסי אכל משחיטת כותי. af Rabbi
Assi achal mishchitat Kuti. And even Rabbi Assi was willing to eat
from the shechting of a כותי. Kuti. ותהה בה רבי זירא. v'tah
bei Rabbi Zeira. And Rabbi Zeira was astounded that they were doing
this after what we had just taught above. And he says, and
he wanted to know and he was wondering the following: either he
said, לא שמיע להו? lo shmiya lehu? They didn't hear this report
that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין beis din invalidated
the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי? Kuti? דאי הוה שמיע להו הוו
מקבלי להו, d'ee hava shmiya lehu hava mekablei lehu, had they heard
this report,
they obviously would have accepted and they wouldn't be eating from the
slaughtering of a כותי. Kuti. That's one possibility, that they never heard
this report of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his בית דין. beis
din. או דילמא, o dilma, or Rabbi Zeira said there's another possibility:
שמיע להו ולא קבלוה. shmiya lehu v'lo kabluha. Maybe they heard the
report and they didn't accept it. Okay, so he didn't know. Here
you had later אמוראים Amoraim eating from the שחיטה Shechita of a
כותי, Kuti, and Rabbi Zeira was saying what happened? We taught that
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said it's forbidden. Either they didn't hear that
report, or they heard it and they didn't accept it. Okay, now
but the גמרא Gemara says from here we can infer though how
Rabbi Zeira is interpreting this ruling that the שחיטה Shechita of a
כותי Kuti is not good. How? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, היכי... heichi... wait
a minute, so the גמרא Gemara says או דילמא או שמיע להו
ולא קבלוה. o dilma o shmiya lehu v'lo kabluha. הדר פשטה לנפשיה,
hadar pashuta l'nafshei, well first let's just finish this point, and then
he before we get back to the reading we brought this in,
then he concluded for himself that it must be מסתברא mistabra it
makes sense, דשמיע להו ולא קבלוה. deshmiya lehu v'lo kabluha. They must
have heard the report but they didn't accept it. Why? דאי סלקא
דעתך d'ee salka da'atchach לא שמיע להו, lo shmiya lehu, if we
were to think that they did not hear the report, that they
actually never got the message that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and his
בית דין beis din forbade it, ואי הוה שמיע להו הוו מקבלי
לה, v'ee hava shmiya lehu hava mekablei lei, and had they heard
it they would have accepted it and wouldn't have eaten the meat,
היכי מסתייעא מילתא למיכל איסורא? heichal mistayei milta l'meichal issura? How could
it ever have happened that God could have allowed it that these
people would have eaten forbidden food? Meaning, if they basically said: yes,
I know
that there's a report that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said the שחיטה
Shechita is not good. But I don't פוסק pasken that way. I
think the שחיטה Shechita is still כשר. kosher. Okay, you're entitled to
פוסק pasken it's כשר kosher if somebody פוסק paskens it's not כשר
kosher and therefore you're eating the meat. That scenario makes sense. But
if were they to have heard that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel made
it forbidden, they would have accepted it and they would have treated
the meat as not כשר kosher and the only reason they're eating
the meat now is because they didn't get the report, they didn't
get the memo, if that's true, how could God have allowed them
to eat meat that they themselves would have considered טריפה treif that
is דריש מית? d'reish meit? Why not? השתא בהמתן של צדיקים hashta
behematan shel tzadikim אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא תקלה על ידם, ein
Hakadosh Baruch Hu meivi takala al yadam, if God doesn't even allow
the animals of צדיקים tzadikim to stumble, צדיקים עצמם לא כל שכן?
tzadikim atzmam lo kol sheken? How much more so God does not
allow צדיקים tzadikim to stumble. What's the idea of animals of צדיקים
tzadikim to stumble? That there's a story with the donkey of פנחס
בן יאיר Pinchas ben Yair which we're going to get to, that
he would not eat, you know, anything that he wasn't allowed to
eat, even a donkey wouldn't. So if the donkeys of צדיקים tzadikim
wouldn't eat, how much more so would God prevent צדיקים tzadikim themselves
from eating non-כשר kosher food. So if they ate it, it must
be that they פוסק paskened it was מותר. mutar. They ruled against
this story, you know, this statement that they forbade the שחיטה Shechita
of a כותי Kuti and they held that it was really okay.
So now what we've seen now is that there is a position
that the שחיטה Shechita of a כותי Kuti is not good even,
you know, even with direct observation, and that's from all the way
back to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, but nevertheless even later אמוראים Amoraim
not everybody accepts it and some people would eat from the שחיטה
Shechita of a כותי Kuti even in the even later. You know,
even generations after, and would disagreed with that ruling and said that
it remained okay as long as, let's say, there was direct observation.
Now, top of ו' עמוד א' vav amud aleph though, getting back
to our question, did רבי זירא, Rebbi Zeira, how did רבי זירא
Rebbi Zeira interpret the ruling of רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? Did he
interpret it with or without a ישראל Yisrael observing it? So now
the גמרא Gemara says the following: ואי סלקא דעתך לא קיבלה מיניה,
ve-ee salka dach-tach lo kibla minei, if רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira did
not accept the response that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is talking about
direct observation, and he wanted to explain that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
was only talking about when it wasn't observed, so why did he
have a whole conniption here about, you know, רבי אסי Rebbi Assi
and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan eating from the שחיטה shchita of a
כותי? kuti? Maybe רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, when they said you can't
trust the שחיטה shchita of a כותי, kuti, was only when it
was not being directly observed. Okay, לשני ליה, lishni lei, why couldn't
he say כאן כשישראל עומד על גבו כאן כשאין ישראל עומד על
גבו, kan keshe-Yisrael omed al gavo kan keshein Yisrael omed al gavo,
that the only time we excluded it was when it was not
being directly observed, but if it was being directly observed, then it
would be okay? So remember, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel had this, there
was a statement: רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said שחיטה shchita of a
כותי kuti not good. So and רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira wanted to
say maybe that only means without observation when it wasn't observed. But
if that if he really held to that, he wouldn't have had
a problem why these other אמוראים Amoraim ate from the שחיטה shchita
of a כותי, kuti, because he could have just said, oh, I
understand why they ate from it because that was when it was
being directly observed. Since he did not have that simple solution, obviously
in the end he accepted the fact that this statement of רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that the שחיטה shchita of a כותי kuti is
not good means in all circumstances, even when it's directly observed. אלא
לאו שמע מינה, ela lav shma mina, we hear from this is,
קיבלה מיניה, kibla minei, he did accept it, שמע מינה, shma mina,
we hear that. Okay, good. So now we are at a position
where there's a clear ruling that the שחיטה shchita of a כותי
kuti is not good, even with direct observation. We don't know why
yet, but we know that that I hinted to you what what
it's about, but that's what we said. And the other position, which
we have yet to say is on the other position, even many
generations after, rejects that and says that the שחיטה shchita of a
כותי kuti is still going to be is still going to be
good, that was רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan and רבי אסי Rebbi Assi
and so on. I want to say one thing, we're going to
get back to this, but about this line that, because we're going
to see it also later in today's דף, daf, that God doesn't
allow the צדיקים, tzadikim, you know, to err. So there's a תוספות
Tosafot here, says what are you talking about, and he brings cases
in the גמרא Gemara where צדיקים tzadikim sin, you know, and because
by mistake, like they they didn't realize whatever it was. So תוספות
Tosafot says no, we're talking very specifically about eating forbidden food. And
whenever the גמרא Gemara says בהמתן של צדיקים צדיקים עצמן לא כל
שכן, behemtan shel tzadikim tzadikim atzman lo kol she-ken, uses this story
of פנחס בן יאיר, Pinchas ben Yair, asks how could this צדיק
tzadik have sinned, God wouldn't have allowed it, it specifically is talking
about forbidden food. And it seems to be because of this idea
that then we're not just talking about sin, then we're talking about
something forbidden going into your body. And that is seen to be
more problematic than just the sin itself, but somehow has some corrupting
effect, you know, physical or even more spiritual on your body. Now,
that's important because that leads to a whole approach in הלכה halacha
about how much is do we treat forbidden food as just any
sin, or do we treat it as some objective wrong even if
it's not about sin. And one, for example, example is, how about
feeding infants or feeding infants non-kosher food, or at least allowing them
to eat non-kosher food? So if they're doing other things, you don't
stop your baby from, I don't know, turning on the lights on
שבת, Shabbat, right? If he's an infant, not the age of חינוך.
chinuch. Is food different? Is somehow טריף treif food seen as having
this corrupting effect that goes beyond just the prohibition? So that's an
interesting area that gets discussed, but that's obviously what's being echoed here
that they can't imagine that a צדיק tzadik would eat non-kosher food
even though sometimes a צדיק tzadik does do other types of things,
you know, sins by error. So back to that.